(字幕組:我已經等了很久)
OK 早安
今天我們會說
Waiting
From the ascension of Jesus
to the arrival of the Holy Spirit
我們上次呢
Pastor Gavin 跟我們說了
Acts 1 第一集
然後呢 今天我們會說
第二集 是不是
發生了什麼事呢?
Jesus has died
Jesus 死了 然後復活
然後呢 就升了到天堂
我們看到那一幅圖
Jesus ascended into heaven
然後 主耶穌
未升到天堂之前呢
祂跟門徒說了什麼呢?
祂就跟他們說
我們看Acts 1
Do not leave Jerusalem
But wait for my gift
from my Father promised
For the gift my Father promised
Which you have heard me speak about
耶穌跟那些門徒說了什麼呢?
你等候一個禮物
這個禮物是誰來的?
是誰來的?
是聖靈
你回去Jerusalem
去等候聖靈來
OK 那些門徒呢
就等了 是不是?
那我們今天問一下
你們大家
你們等候什麼呢?
你們在等什麼呢?
What are you waiting for?
說一下 你今天在等什麼呢?
Holiday
OK
Karen想去
對了 你
叫什麼名字呢?
Alias
Alias 你等候什麼呢?
吃飯
很餓 這個
還沒吃早餐 是不是?
Samantha 你等候什麼呢?
Boyfriend
哇
Samantha 等候Boyfriend
OK
Samantha 等候什麼呢?
考完試 是不是?
有Summer Holiday
Erica呢?
你等候什麼呢?
沒什麼等
OK
Lucas呢?
Lucas 你等候什麼呢?
不知道
Gabriel呢?
你等候什麼呢?
OK
我等候他 其實
有些人呢 就等著Summer Holiday 是不是?
有些人等著 想去Travel 是不是?
誰想去等Travel的?
OK 沒人想Travel
有些人呢 想等
考試Exam的Resort
有沒有人等著Exam Resort的?
還沒考 還沒考
OK 快要等了
有些人呢 就進大學
等著Acceptance的 有沒有?
Sophia有 OK
Erica進了
Samantha 等著回大學
去University of Calgary
有些人呢 就等著他開始
Career在哪裡?
有些人呢 就在找
有些學生呢 就在找他的Career Path在哪裡
你們找了 你想去的Career Path在哪裡?
知不知道?
有沒有? Gabriel 有沒有找到你
想去的Career Path?
想做什麼?
全服音 Very good
可能讀神學 是不是?
那Nathan呢? Nathan想開始讀什麼?
他還在等神 去帶領他
去什麼Career Path OK
有些人呢 就受傷了
好像Lebron James那樣 是不是?
他High Ankle Sprain
你知不知道他受傷了多久?
休息了多久?
差不多一個月了 是不是?
他等候 等候什麼?
Healing Waiting for Healing OK
那我們為什麼要等呢?
Why do we wait?
我看到有Two main reasons
第一呢 是我們Uncontrollable reasons
我們沒有 沒得Control的
第二呢 是Controllable reasons
OK 那有什麼是我們可以有能力
沒有能力去控制到的 Reason呢?
是 Negative Unforeseen Changes
是不是? 有什麼 Negative Unforeseen Changes
是我們不能控制到的?
有什麼?
COVID 是不是?
有Pandemic 我們Control不到
是不是? 那Pandemic呢?
有我們不能Travel
有我們學校有不同的Testing System
有Mock Exam 有什麼
不知道什麼Prediction of your grades 是不是?
是Unpredictable的 有時是Negative的
還有什麼? 是不能控制到的
Negative 不能控制到的Changes
還有什麼? Anything else?
還有什麼?
意外 是不是?
Sometimes we have accidents
有沒有一些Family member or friend聽過
或者News聽過 有一些Accident 是不是?
有時有意外呢 我們就Uncontrollable 是不是?
有時我們身體有Health Issue
有沒有人身體Experience一些Health Issue 是不是?
或者我們打球有時 是不是?
可能有意外
好像LeBron James那樣
我經常打球都有很多不同的Accident
有不同的Injury 是不是?
如果你上班呢
你Working full time 可能有Layoff
有沒有人聽過 有些人是Layoff了
有沒有Layoff 是不是?
Uncontrollable Negative Changes
這些Uncontrollable Negative Changes
發生的時候 我們就要等候神 是不是?
有Pandemic 我們要等候神
我們身體有不同的Issue
我們病了 又要等候神
這個小朋友受傷了
就要等候神去醫好他
Gabriel之前都有不同的Health Issue
他又要等候神 是不是?
Gabriel
我們每個人都會有時去Experience
我們控制不到的
Negative, Uncontrollable, Unforeseen Changes
但有時是Positive 是不是?
有什麼是Positive, Uncontrollable Reasons
我們是要等的
有沒有人想到什麼是Positive?
剛才我們想了Negative
現在有沒有Positive?
沒有嗎?
Come on 幫幫忙吧
OK 有時呢
嘩 你很厲害呀這個東西
你可不可以來幫忙我們的Company呀?
有些人Recruit你
有沒有人被我Recruit了
去上班 或者去拍攝
Karen有 拍照
嘩 Karen 你拍照那麼厲害
我看到你IG很厲害
你幫我拍下照吧 是不是?
還有可能Gabriel
你彈琴很厲害
或者Erica
你彈Cello很厲害
我Recruit你去幫忙
是不是? 幫忙Samantha
以後的婚禮 是不是?
你幫忙去彈 是不是?
這些是Positive Opportunity
我們控制不了的
但有人去給你Positive Opportunity
還有可能我們Government
嘩 Pandemic
但他給了我們有些Subsidy 有錢
可以去Samantha
你們Erica Sofia
你們Spend了$10,000
用了什麼?
Saving 嘩 這些女生很厲害
很厲害 懂得Save
有時我們有Scholarship
學校有沒有Scholarship?
有沒有試過有Scholarship?
大學有沒有Scholarship?
這些是Positive Uncontrollable Reason
有時 第一是Uncontrollable
沒有控制不了的Reason
有些是Controllable 是不是?
什麼是Controllable Positive Reason
我們要等候的 有時
Samantha 你Apply了什麼?
Apply了大學 有不同的Opportunity
那我就等UBC Calgary Bristol
還有什麼學校?
我Apply了大學
但我要等候結果
他收不收我?
有時你轉學校
你在High School轉學校
你Apply一個新學校
但要等候
等他們認不認識我們
有時我們參加
或者Apply 或者Tryout
for 這些Sports Team
是不是? Nathan 你之前有沒有
Apply Tryout 這些Sports Team?
沒有 沒有Tryout
它是Uncontrollable的Reason
它是Recruit 它的
有沒有人Tryout過
它的Basketball Team
Football Team
Lucas 是不是有Football Team?
你Tryout什麼Team?
Football Team
Football Team很厲害
你Tryout的時候
又要等候
Coach可能選你
入個Team
有時選不到
你選不選到?
入了
好 恭喜你
有時我們Apply新的工作
Part-Time Job
你有沒有Part-Time Job
Apply過的?
有沒有?
Sophia 什麼Part-Time Job?
你Apply了?
Church!
OK! Yeah! 你等候
D牧師
看看人收不收你
Deacons 收不收你
OK! Yes!
這些是Positive
Controllable Reason
你是Apply中的
但有時呢
我們呢
就會做Mistake
這些是Controllable Reason
但有Mistake
有沒有人做了Mistake?
有沒有人忘記有Test
或者Assignment?
有沒有人忘記了Hand in
有Test 或者Assignment?
沒有?
你們有沒有?
有的 是不是?
忘記了
有Test
然後Last Minute
是不是?
嘩! 要考試
那怎麼辦?
或者忘記了
忘記了Hand in Assignment
哎呀! 不知道怎麼辦
有時我們做錯了
就有後果了
是不是?
這個後果呢
就要可能祈禱
哎呀! 神啊! 你幫幫我吧
我忘記了考試
或者忘記了Hand in Assignment
有後果
不知道
可能肥了這個
這個Course
有時呢
我們犯罪
都要有後果的
是不是? 我們犯罪有沒有試過有後果?
有沒有Result?
沒有啊?
你們犯罪的時候有話說嗎?
嘩! 神很Bless你啊!
有時我們可能說錯話
傷害到別人
是不是? 有沒有人試過說錯話
說謊話
或者傷害到別人
傷害到別人的時候
然後那個Other Person又怎樣?
可能很傷心
是不是?
這個時間呢
有時是要Wait的
要Wait
祈禱
希望神會Forgive我
希望那個人又Forgive我
是不是?
這些是Controllable Reasons
但是我們犯錯了
我們犯錯的時候
就有時要等候的
OK
那我們
Go Through了一些Reason
為什麼我們要等候
為什麼Why do we Wait
我們每個人呢
都有三個Scenario的
OK
這個三個Scenario是In a Trial
是不是?
In a Trial
我有意外
我訂了
我做錯了
我忘記了Hand in an Assignment
Apply University
I'm in a Trial
是不是?
我要等候神
我要祈禱
神啊! 你幫我啊!
我做錯了
或者我等候University
你帶領我去哪個Direction
是不是?
去這個University
或者這個Direction
去不同的University
有時呢
我們完了一個Trial
就I'm just out of a Trial
然後第三個Scenario呢
我們就要進去
Another Trial
Going into Another Trial
OK
那你們
今天是什麼情況呢?
誰是In a Trial的?
你舉起手
誰覺得自己是In a Trial的?
OK
還有誰呢?
你覺得不是
OK
Just out of a Trial
誰是Just out of a Trial的?
OK
沒有人
Going into a Next Trial
覺得自己是Going into a Next Trial
有沒有?
沒有
誰是不知道自己是在什麼情況?
OK
你們不知道自己是在什麼情況
Samantha
你剛剛
是不是?
等候了神
進了大學
那你可能Just out of a Trial
是不是?
Just out of a Trial
OK
我們每個人呢
都是有一個情況的
OK
那之前呢
我們讀了Acts 1
那些門徒呢
都是有一個情況的
是不是?
他們的情況是什麼呢?
我們看看
他們不同的情況
他們的領袖呢
是誰呢?
他們的領袖是主耶穌
祂死了
復活了
然後又升上天堂
然後呢
他們又可能混淆了
是不是?
主耶穌真的是誰呢?
祂是神來的
祂剛剛升上天堂
然後
祂是不是下個星期回來呢?
是不是幾天又回來呢?
還是很久才回來呢?
他們混淆了
是不是?
他們有點混淆
主耶穌是誰呢?
祂什麼時候會回來呢?
他們都不是很清楚
是不是?
然後呢
他們又不是很清楚
聖靈是誰呢?
聖靈會來
Jesus說
但是祂會來幫我們什麼呢?
祂會教我們什麼呢?
祂會領我們去做什麼呢?
我不是很清楚
是不是?
然後呢
他們都很害怕
那些羅曼斯
是不是?
那些羅曼斯可能是去
找他們
這些是主耶穌的門徒
祂在哪裡?
找他們出來
他們有沒有搞事?
是不是?
他們跟隨主耶穌
他們之前可能跟隨主耶穌去搞事
是不是?
所以這些門徒
是在受審嗎?
還是只是在被審問?
是不是?
這些門徒
都是很迷茫的
在這個時間
那麼
這個迷茫
這個受審的時間
這些門徒做了什麼呢?
他們等候的時候
他們做了什麼呢?
你猜他們做了什麼?
你猜啊
什麼?
上班?
是不是回去釣魚?
我們等候神
剛剛主耶穌
上了天
我回去釣魚
是不是?
可能啊
可能
我們看看
第一章第二段
第二章第一章的第二段
然後聖徒們
一起讀
英文
1,2,3
然後聖徒們回到耶穌基督的教堂
從山頂的
聖母塔
在聖誕節時
他們從城裡走來
他們到達時
他們走到房間
他們住的房間
那些人在場的
是彼得
約翰
詹姆斯和安德魯
菲利普和托馬斯
巴爾多拉米爾和馬丁
詹姆斯
埃爾維亞斯和塞門德塞勒
和朱德斯
詹姆斯的兒子
他們都在祈禱中
不斷地聚在一起
與女人在一起
與耶穌的母親
和他的兄弟結婚
我們看到
門徒們在做什麼?
在這個審訊的時間
他們做了什麼?
答案在這裡
他們在聽
主耶穌叫他們做什麼?
耶穌叫他們去耶路撒冷
去等什麼?
去等聖靈
等聖靈來到
等待耶穌
他們在聽耶穌的指令
耶穌的聖靈會來
他們在聽
他們在聽耶穌的指令
第二
他們做什麼?
Samantha剛剛說的
奉行
然後就是祈禱
在第14:13說
他們在祈禱中不斷地聚在一起
他們在祈禱
等候主耶穌說的聖靈來
他們不斷地等待
不斷地在祈禱
第一他們是奉行的
第二是祈禱
第二他們是怎樣?
我們繼續讀
Peter stood up among the believers and said
Brothers and sisters, the scripture has been fulfilled
in which the Holy Spirit spoke long ago
through David concerning Judas
who served as a guide for those who arrested Jesus
He was one of our number and shared in our ministry
Four, Peter said
It is written in the book of Psalms
My place has been deserted
Let there be no one to dwell in it
May another take his place of leadership
Peter then read the Bible
The Old Testament
What did he see?
He saw a prophecy
that someone would betray Jesus
Who would betray Jesus?
Judas
We read it before
Judas son of James
was not the same Judas who betrayed Jesus
Do you know what happened after Judas betrayed Jesus?
What did he do?
He committed suicide
He hung himself
He was so ashamed or embarrassed or suffering
Suffering through what he had done
Judas betrayed Jesus and he hung himself
Peter saw the Old Testament
He said, "OK"
The Old Testament predicted
The Holy Spirit predicted
that this event would happen
Jesus would be betrayed
But what would happen to us?
He saw it in Psalms
May his place be deserted
Let no one dwell in his place
And may another take the place of leadership
May another take the place of leadership
They saw in the Old Testament
What is the leadership of God?
Leading them to recruit another person
To take their place
We see in this passage
Peter looked into Scripture as the foundation
They waited for God
What did they do?
They read the Bible
They saw the Old Testament
The Old Testament predicted that this event would happen
What should we do?
We should recruit another person
Another person to take his place
OK
Third, when they waited for the Holy Spirit
What did they do?
They looked for God's leading
Therefore, it says in verse 21
It is necessary to choose one of the men
Who have been with us the whole time
The Lord Jesus was living among us
So they nominated two men
Joseph and another called Matthias
They prayed, "Lord, you know everyone's heart
Show us which of these two
You have chosen to take over this ministry"
They cast lots
The lot fell on Matthias
He was added to the eleven apostles
What did they do?
They prayed
They waited for God to lead them
They looked for God's leading
They prayed, "Lord, you know everyone's heart
You know our hearts
Show us which of these two men you have chosen"
They looked for God's leading
OK
The disciples
Let's recap
In the next slide
What did the disciples do?
The first is they obeyed and they prayed
They obeyed and they prayed
They went to Jerusalem
They waited for the Holy Spirit
Then they were constantly in prayer
Constantly in prayer
Then they read the Bible
They read the Old Testament
They read the Bible
The prophets predicted this event
Then what?
They waited for God's leading
They looked for God's leading
God, you lead us
Which disciple to choose
To take over this ministry
The fourth is we see in this scripture
They have a supportive community
They have a supportive ministry
When they wait for the Holy Spirit
OK
Now we will invite Lucas to speak his testimony
Let's give him a round of applause
Lucas, come up and speak your testimony
Hello
I will talk about how I wait for God
It was about a year ago
I was a transfer student
I was in the 7th grade
I was in the 2nd grade
I was bullied all the time
I was beaten
I was thrown away
I was kicked and beaten
It was painful
I was like this every day
I went back to school
I couldn't read
I walked away
My books were scattered
I went to the toilet
I was on the floor
It was painful
I prayed to God
God, I feel so bad
Can you let me go?
I feel so bad
Nothing happened
I was beaten
I was kicked and pushed to the wall
I was kicked and kicked on the stairs
I was kicked on the stairs
I was scared
I felt unsafe going back to school
My teacher didn't help me
I didn't care
I was unhappy
I was in the 8th grade
It was like this
There was a teacher
She was my teacher
She always targeted me
She threw my books outside
It was a mountain outside
I couldn't pick them up
I went back to the classroom
I said, "Teacher, my books were thrown away"
She yelled at me
What excuse is that?
How dare you to lie to me?
I was punished
Detention
I was sent to the detention
For 3 or 4 times
Wow!
You were punished by a classmate
Your teacher treated you like this
Wow!
I cried
I prayed to God
I asked the teacher
I said, "Teacher, I'm in pain
Can you help me?
I'm so unhappy"
It was like this
I was punished
I didn't change anything
I had to avoid it
I had to walk away
Even my friends
They didn't dare to play with me
One of my friends told me
She said, "I can't play with you"
Why?
Because if I play with you
I'll be punished
I can't play with you
If I'm punished, I'll be scolded
I can't do that
Wow!
I cried
I thought
I was back to school
I was punished
I was scolded
The teachers criticized me
Once
On the wedding website
Someone wrote my name
They scolded me
They asked me why I went there
Of course, I was punished
I thought
You punished me
The teachers punished me
My classmates punished me
Even my friends left me
Wow!
I cried
I prayed to God
I told God
Let me go
I don't want to stay here
One year passed
Year 9
I was scolded again
Then, the pandemic came
The pandemic was good
I didn't have to go to school
My grades improved
Everything improved
I went back to school
I told my dad
I couldn't go back
Let me go
He said
Let's wait
I prayed to God
Wow!
God, let me go
I couldn't go back
I was in school everyday
Then
Something strange happened
Someone wanted to punish me
Then
I was punished
Someone found the evidence
He wanted to punish me again
Then he showed it to the principal
The principal scolded me
He said
No evidence
This is only what they said
They didn't do it yet
So
They shouldn't get anything
You're just thinking too much
He scolded me
I was surprised
I thought
I couldn't go back
Even my classmates didn't help me
Even the teachers didn't help me
Then
Dad scolded him
He was fine
He scolded him
But nothing happened
The people didn't get punished
I was fine
Then
Dad finally said
Son
I'll help you
I finally went to see
Then
I found a school
EU Chow International School
I applied
I remember that day
I had an interview
I had to do an exam
I went in
I sat there
I prayed for God
I said
God
Please protect me
Let me go to school
I really want to go to school
I don't want to be bullied
Beaten
And so on
Then
OK
I did it
I didn't hear from them for a month
No news for two months
Then
They sent me an email
They said
I could do a second interview
I could interview the principal
I had two principals
I did the interview
I felt good
But
I didn't hear from them for a while
Then
One day
It was strange
The parents
Asked me a question
They said
If I was accepted
Would you go to school?
I said
I don't know
God said
But I really wanted to go to school
I felt bad
I was bullied
Then
I was accepted
Wow
I cried
I thanked God
I thought
This is the time
I finally came
I waited for three years
From year 7
To year 10
Then I left
Now I feel good
At least I went to school
I am good with my friends
I don't have to go to school
I don't have to carry anything
If I leave it for two minutes
I will lose everything
I thank God
I can go to a new school
Thank you
Thank you, Lucas
Lucas, welcome back to our
Titus English Team
So it's very good
Thank you for sharing, Lucas
We know
You had a difficult experience
Right?
You were bullied at school
And your teacher didn't help
But we can see that
He is waiting for God
He prayed
He waited for God
Do you want to give me different opportunities?
New opportunity
To go to different schools
Let's ask ourselves
When we wait
Do we pray?
When we wait for God
Do we have different trials?
Do we read the Bible?
To wait for God
To give us direction from His Word
When we wait for God
Do we ask God to lead us?
To give us direction
And when we wait for God
Do we have a supportive community
To help us?
Right?
Lucas has his parents to support him
We have different trials
Different times
We have to wait
Do we have a supportive Christian community?
Like the doors are together
We are constantly in prayer
I remember
I have been in Hong Kong for 3.5 years
I served in Hong Kong
So fast
I have known you guys for 3.5 years
But before I came to Hong Kong
I was a trainee in 2016
In Hong Kong Buddhist Institute
After I was a trainee
I went back to Canada
To study in Catholic University
To finish my seminary
Then the Hong Kong Buddhist Institute invited me
Do you want to come back to serve?
We are full time
I was thinking in 2017
The next slide is the picture of Hong Kong
I was thinking
God, do you really want to bring me back to Hong Kong to serve?
Right?
Back to Hong Kong
It was very hot in the summer
My friends were in Canada
My family and parents were in Toronto
Back to Hong Kong to serve
There were different trials
Different challenges
I prayed
God, do you really want to lead me to Hong Kong to serve?
If yes, may you open doors
Continue to open doors
Right?
Where do you live?
Do you live with your family?
Or do you have different opportunities to live in different places?
God provided a temporary stay for two months in Tai Kwun
God provided there
God provided the opportunity to serve in Hong Kong
Pastor John, the English service, the lead pastor
He encouraged me to come back
Everything lined up
I asked God to open doors
He opened all the doors
I looked into scripture
Scripture says in Isaiah
You will hear a voice saying to you
Look to the left or to the right
You will hear a voice
Go to this direction
I asked God
God, lead me
Give me a clear sign
When I was reading his word
He gave me this passion for people in Hong Kong
And obviously my parents were also very supportive
我的爸爸媽媽很鼓勵我
To support me to come back to Hong Kong to serve
And so
What are you waiting for?
Today maybe you are healing
受傷了
Maybe you are physically injured
Maybe you are emotionally injured
And you are waiting for God to heal you
Will you pray?
Will you read scripture?
Will you ask God for his leading?
Maybe today you are like Lucas
And you are going through things at school
And it is very hard
And you are asking God to help you
God is there
He knows your heart
He knows what you are going through
Will you pray?
What is prayer?
Prayer is us humbling ourselves
謙卑
是不是?
神知道我們會pray什麼
但我們pray的時候
我們的attitude是什麼?
我們的attitude is humbling ourselves before God
As we pray
We humble ourselves before an almighty powerful God
As we look to scripture
What is scripture?
Scripture is our foundation
And so when we wait
We need foundation
A strong foundation
第三是什麼?
As we wait
We need God's leading
Sometimes we need to wait
我們要等候神
門徒也要等候
聖靈主耶穌帶我們
To choose which disciple
Sam之前也要choose
神你帶我去哪個university
Lucas是要等候
你是否帶我去這個新的學校
這個新的opportunity
Surrendering ourselves to God
第四
我們等候神的時候
我們需要一個支持的社區
一群徒弟
父母支持我們
親朋好友是信徒
他們會幫助我們
在等候的時間
我們會謙虛地祈禱嗎?
我們會看著我們的基礎
那就是石矢嗎?
我們會看著神
和聖靈帶領我們嗎?
我們會如何發展社區嗎?
我們請我們的慈悲團隊
一起祈禱
神父
我們感謝您
對於文書
這段話在《聖刀》中
我們感謝您
讓徒弟們等候
祢的聖靈
他們祈禱
他們遵守
他們看著您的文書
他們等候您的呼喚
他們發展社區
我祈禱在我們的情況
不管我們處於什麼情況
無論我們在牢裡
還是在牢裡
無論我們在等什麼
祢會幫助我們
做到一樣的事
我們在耶穌的名下祈禱